hey what's up guys my name is Shawn and
welcome back to my state boss boss
series so today we're gonna be talking
all about unions in C++ so a union is a
little bit like a class type like a
struct type except it can only occupy
the memory of like one member at a time
what that means is that typically if we
have a struct and we declare let's just
say four floats or something in it that
means that we can have four times four
bytes which is a total of 16 bytes and
that's dropped that's how much space it
occupies because we have four members
and obviously as you keep adding more
members to a class or a struct the size
keeps growing a union can only have one
member so if I were if I was to declare
four floats like a b c d the size of the
union would still be four bytes and when
i try to address either a like if i try
to change the value of a or b or c or d
it would literally be the same memory so
if i change a and set it to 5 the value
of d would also be fine that's how
unions work and you can use them exactly
like you can use structs or classes like
you can add like static functions to
them and just normal functions and Men
and methods to them and all of that
stuff however you can't like have
virtual methods and there are some other
restrictions but usually what people use
unions for is very kind of closely
linked to type planning which is what we
did in last bit in the last video so if
you haven't check that out definitely
check that out right now
but it's really useful for when you want
to basically be able to either give two
different names to the same variable
like for example if I had like a
mathematical vector class X Y Z avec 3 I
might also want to address it as if it
was a color RGB right XYZ RGB how can I
get it so that I can use it both ways
and basically you know X will align with
aa and J will align with dull with Y and
all that kind of stuff that's that's all
achievable through the use of a union so
we'll take a look at some examples here
usually I would say that unions are used
anonymously which means your give them a
name and you definitely don't have like
methods or anything in the movement
can't have that if they're not anonymous
but overall unions are really really
useful and we'll just take a look a few
examples to see how we can use them so
I've got some code already written out
here but we'll get to that in a minute
if we just take a look at a basic
example of a union let's just say let's
just say that I'm gonna write an
anonymous Union here we write it the
same way as we kind of deal with a
struct like an anonymous struct but it's
called a union and then I can give it
two different variables let's just say
I'll give it a float a and then int B so
what this means is that if this was a
struct we just have two different
members however what we have here
instead is two different ways to address
the same memory which means that if I
was to say put this into like a struct
called I don't know Union this might
confuse things hopefully not and do
something like this if I was to make an
instance of this Union class and then
said you don't a 22.0 app or something
like that if I go ahead and print the
value of youdo a and you don't be like
this
five then you can see that what we get
here is two and then one zero seven blah
blah because this value is the bio
representation of two as a float if that
makes sense so it's as if we took that
memory that made up the float and then
just interpreted it as it was an int so
we've typed punted basically so that's
what you can use unions for that's what
they are commonly used towards just a
way of type honey if I wants to try and
convert it into two different variable
type something or something like that I
could easily do that so let's take a
little bit more useful example what I've
got up here is essentially a vector to
an effective for now I've also got a
function called print vector two which
takes in a vector two and prints it now
at the moment I can't print two vector
four however you can see that a vector
four is really just two vector twos or
at least that might be one way to look
at it I mean it's got four floats this
has two floats why can't we just see
this vector 4 as two vector twos well
what we could do if we wanted to again
get the vector 2 out out of this thing
is we could do something like you know
get I don't know we'll call this first
part a and then the second part B so the
vector
to a would be X&Y and they would be 7w
we could do something like this where we
construct a whole Effect 2 or something
like that and then give it some members
and return that whole thing and we could
do something like that however that's
going to create a whole new object and
we don't really want to do that we could
also type on our way into this by not
having to copy anything we still will
need to copy something because of the
creating a whole new type but what we
could do instead is just return a
reference to a vector which is really
just a type on version of X so the way
that we would do that is we would cast
the memory address of X to a vector 2
like that and then dereference it so you
get this right and that could be one way
of doing that but another way of doing
that is by using a Union and that will
probably look a lot better as well so to
do that I'm just going to get rid of
this function and then wrap this in a
Union so a union as we know and I'll
just get rid of the name because it's
going to be an anonymous Union a Union
as you know can only have one member so
we can't just leave the float X by the W
like this because that would mean that X
Y Z and W would both occupy that same
for by space what we need to do is
actually wrap this in an anonymous
struct like this so I'll just say struct
and then put that float XY the W in
there like that so now this struct is is
the one kind of member that the Union
has wishes which happens to be like a
sixteen by structure now at this point
nothing's changed right if I go ahead
and let's actually create a vector two
or rather I'll create a vector four I'll
just call it vector and I'll set it
equal to one two three four I can still
access vector dot X and whatever like
normal right I can set this to like two
or whatever I can still access it as
usual because like I haven't given this
a name or any thought that if I start
doing that it's gonna grow everything
but if it's an anonymous thing it's just
really just a way to kind of structure
the data it's not really adding anything
but again the benefit here is that it's
converting all this into a single member
which is what the Union expects and
finally I'll make another struct here so
obviously this is adding a second member
to the Union which means that it's going
to occupy the same space as this first
member and that's going to consist of
two dr. twos
just like that okay so now I have a few
ways of accessing this data inside back
to four I can in it I can either use X Y
Z W or I can use a and B and a will be
the same memory as x and Y and B will be
the same memory set in W so let's check
out how that can work so I've got one
two three four written down here what
I'll do is I'll print vector to our
print vector dot a okay just to get that
result out and then I'll set vector dot
we'll want to know let's just say vector
dog's Zed
I'll set equal to 500 and then I'll
print it after two but this time I'll
print event above be one factor probably
might be useful to print both of them
both times just for fun again I also
have a little bit of a divider I guess
so that is clear when we actually
modified the Domino inside I'll click
done so let's take a look at this okay
so check that out we have one two three
four as we would expect the first time
and then one to 504 so I haven't even
touched the actual be part of that
vector obviously I haven't said B dot X
to 500 I've said vector dot Z to 500
which is actually this variable here but
this variable here corresponds to B dot
X because it's occupy because it's
occupying the same memory okay so
hopefully that's a pretty good example
of how unions work again they're really
useful when you want to do stuff like
this when you have multiple or when you
want multiple ways to address that same
data because it might be useful in a
number of ways again you could use type
planning or something like this usually
unions are much more readable there can
be some problems that come out of this
which we might talk about in another
video but I don't like talking about
that kind of stuff because it's some of
those I just like very unlikely to
happen and you'll probably be fine but
anyway hopefully that will give you the
confidence you need I hope you guys
enjoy this video if you did you know
it's a like button let me know
patreon.com force us to share our best
way to support the series huge thank you
as always to all the lovely patrons who
made this possible leave any comments
you have below about like unions why you
use them why you want
use them or why bet why they've been
useful to you I'll see you guys in the
next video goodbye
[Music]